<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Gatsby Starter Blog RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[My personal blogpage.]]></description><link>https://ckvignesh.github.io</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 16:23:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Open Source and 100 Days of Code - Week 1 Update]]></title><description><![CDATA[Prologue My first attempt at #100DaysOfCode was back in October 2021. It also coincided with the Hacktoberfest 2021 (which was in October…]]></description><link>https://ckvignesh.github.io/100dayscode-week-one/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://ckvignesh.github.io/100dayscode-week-one/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;Prologue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first attempt at #100DaysOfCode was back in October 2021. It also coincided with the Hacktoberfest 2021 (which was in October). I started contributing to Open Source without really intending to. I saw a Repo that had some missing links and just wanted to let the maintainer/owner know the updated one. That was my first OS Contribution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written about it in my first Hashnode article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ckvignesh.hashnode.dev/my-first-pull-request-that-was-merged-and-why-you-must-contribute-to-open-source&quot;&gt;My first Pull Request that was merged and why you must contribute to Open Source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I had to abandon it after 19 days of a continuous coding streak. I did 21 days where the last 2 days were after an interruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
![image.png](https://cdn.hashnode.com/res/hashnode/image/upload/v1642821715305/9AmzJFb2g.png)
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.hashnode.com/res/hashnode/image/upload/v1642821919234/KxojSsDxl.png&quot; alt=&quot;Git Graph 1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not burned out but, just skipped a couple of days after the 21st day and lost continuity. It was around the same time that my back started aching as I was spending late nights and weekends sitting on my bed, learning to code. That was a bad idea and I refrained from doing that again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I was not successful in finishing the challenge in that attempt, it helped me customize my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ckvignesh&quot;&gt;Github landing page&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#x26; build a resume website. I became better at using Git and Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the most important part - I rediscovered my passion for programming thanks to supportive communities. I also found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/eduardovedes&quot;&gt;Mentor&lt;/a&gt; to help me progress faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t stress the importance of getting a community and a mentor to support and guide you in this process. The learning that happens in a cohort can’t be replicated in an isolated study environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I had set up a good environment to get into coding &amp;#x26; also got some like-minded people to travel with. The journey had become easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning 0.0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Programmers, we are accustomed to starting things with 0. It’s theoretically relevant too since I had to restart. So here’s what I learned during my first attempt. Some of them are documented as blogs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ckvignesh.hashnode.dev/github-submodules-and-how-you-can-use-them-for-your-projects&quot;&gt;Github Submodules and how you can use them for your Projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ckvignesh.hashnode.dev/configuring-githubs-personal-access-token-to-make-code-pushes-easier&quot;&gt;Configuring Github’s Personal Access Token to Make Code Pushes Easier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved my CSS knowledge by playing some games like &lt;a href=&quot;https://flexboxfroggy.com/&quot;&gt;Flexbox Froggy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://codepip.com/games/grid-garden/&quot;&gt;Grid Garden&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#x26; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flexboxdefense.com/&quot;&gt;Flex Box Defense&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Innings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took some time to re-organize everything after I abandoned my first attempt at the #100DaysofCode. I restarted it in the last week of December 2021. Since there was a gap of more than a month between my first attempt and the second one, I decided to start from 0 rather than continue it from where I left off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, even the 2nd attempt was not easy. I could not code consistently because of too much “context-switching”. There were a lot of factors that distracted me. I took care of all that in December &amp;#x26; sorted it out. After that, I took a week’s break and resumed the #100DaysOfCode challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
![image.png](https://cdn.hashnode.com/res/hashnode/image/upload/v1642822047094/DjoV7YOY6.png)
*Please don&apos;t mind the inconsistency in the `Longest Streak` figures here and above. It was caused by me deleting a Repo I was working on, at that time.*
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning 1.0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began to rethink my strategy during the second attempt of #100DaysOfCode. The main intention of the #100DaysofCode challenge was to learn consistently and move ahead to get a developer job. It need not be &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Coding&lt;/code&gt; as such, every day. It could be something like reading documentation, books and papers or solving some mathematical problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read Tiia’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.tiia.rocks/making-100daysofcode-work-for-me-with-new-rules&quot;&gt;Making #100DaysOfCode work for me with new rules&lt;/a&gt; around that time which had an overlap with my thoughts. There are a few more points in her article and I agree with those since it aligns with the goal of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;getting consistently better at programming&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I joined the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freecodecamp.org/&quot;&gt;freecodecamp&lt;/a&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;2022 Become-a-Dev New Year&apos;s Resolution Challenge which overlaps with the #100DaysOfCode Challenge&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Take the 2022 Become-a-Dev New Year&amp;#39;s Resolution Challenge:&lt;br&gt;📊Max your stats in &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/LearnToCodeRPG?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#LearnToCodeRPG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;⌨️Start &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/100DaysOfCode?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#100DaysOfCode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;🛢️Finish the fCC Relational Databases Cert&lt;br&gt;📜Publish 3 tutorials on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashnode?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@Hashnode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;To accept: quote-retweet this saying &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m in.&amp;quot; I&amp;#39;ll add you to my Twitter list. 🧵&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Quincy Larson (@ossia) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ossia/status/1476581551873925123?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;December 30, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started playing the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Learn To Code RPG&lt;/code&gt; Game (which was a part of the 2022 Become-a-Dev New Year’s Resolution Challenge). Corrected a typo in the game. (Not that important but, it was a good exercise). I would tell every aspiring developer to play that game before you start learning to code. I’ve written why you should, here:
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/100DaysOfCode?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#100DaysOfCode&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Day 3: I had to pause my &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/100daysofcode?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#100daysofcode&lt;/a&gt; for close to a week as I got caught up with some personal stuff.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I played the RPG game of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/freeCodeCamp?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@freeCodeCamp&lt;/a&gt; when I got some time over the last week&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Managed to get the stats here.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But there are a few important lessons... &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/SLTDRJ6hCI&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/SLTDRJ6hCI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Vignesh | Programmer | Writer (@vigneshCodes) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vigneshCodes/status/1482058649191469056?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 14, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attempted quizzes at &lt;a href=&quot;https://developerquiz.org/&quot;&gt;Learn to Code RPG&lt;/a&gt; Quiz website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revisited freecodecamp’s Javascript Learning Path.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started working on a few personal React Projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started learning &lt;a href=&quot;https://remix.run/&quot;&gt;Remix&lt;/a&gt; to build a website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An idea for a new Open Source Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began to pen down a book, which was about something I started thinking since December 2020. My first attempts to write it were on Google Docs. It was fine till I wrote about 5000 words. After that, it became difficult to organize and re-order chapters in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, I discovered some specific tools for authors. I made some notes after researching about it here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ckvignesh.hashnode.dev/writing-tools-for-your-next-book&quot;&gt;Writing Tools For Your Next Book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some free tools and some paid ones too. I chose &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theologeek.ch/manuskript/&quot;&gt;Manuskript&lt;/a&gt; to write my book. I also liked &lt;a href=&quot;https://wavemaker.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Wavemaker&lt;/a&gt; and would recommend that too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were just two of the many awesome Free and Open Source Software for writing books on Linux. But, they had their limitations which is when I realized I needed a better solution for my problem. So that’s when I thought of creating a new tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal would be to create a new OS Project that gives writers an awesome interface to write books. It may take years but, it’ll help a lot of writers who may not be able to afford the expensive proprietary software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ckvignesh/writingApp&quot;&gt;Repo&lt;/a&gt; for it on Github. Feel free to join the discussions and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Resources:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://discord.gg/arhYabfc&quot;&gt;The community where I found my mentor&lt;/a&gt; - @&lt;a href=&quot;@eduardovedes&quot;&gt;Eduardo Vedes&lt;/a&gt;: iamFreeCodeCamp. There are many other stalwarts there. You’re welcome to join &amp;#x26; start your journey.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eddiejaoude.io/course-github-profile-landing&quot;&gt;Course to improve your Github Landing Page&lt;/a&gt;. Eddie also has a wonderful community for Open Source.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Asabeneh/30-Days-Of-JavaScript&quot;&gt;Javascript&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#x26; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Asabeneh/30-Days-Of-React&quot;&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; from scratch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freecodecamp.org/learn/&quot;&gt;freecodecamp’s learning path&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.100daysofcode.com/&quot;&gt;#100DaysOfCode - The Official Website for the Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/2022-become-a-dev-new-years-resolution-challenge/&quot;&gt;Take the 2022 Become-a-Dev New Year’s Resolution Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lessons For Newbie Developers from The War of Art]]></title><description><![CDATA[In October, I challenged myself to take up the #100DaysofCode challenge after I read about Alex Kallaway’s journey on freeCodeCamp. On my…]]></description><link>https://ckvignesh.github.io/war-of-art-review/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://ckvignesh.github.io/war-of-art-review/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In October, I challenged myself to take up the #100DaysofCode challenge after I read about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/the-crazy-history-of-the-100daysofcode-challenge-and-why-you-should-try-it-for-2018-6c89a76e298d/&quot;&gt;Alex Kallaway’s journey&lt;/a&gt; on freeCodeCamp. On my journey, I have faced many ups and downs. Some parts of the journey were easy and some were really hard. But, I never stopped learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becoming a software developer is no easy job. It’s a continuous journey of learning. When the journey is easy, it’s a pleasure to travel. But, the real test of grit, perseverance and patience takes place when the odds are against you. That’s when I came across an article by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/learning-to-code-when-it-gets-dark-e485edfb58fd/#.yjh0fehje&quot;&gt;Alex Kallaway&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe most developers out there are self-taught (at least most of the ones I personally know).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;The best engineers I’ve worked with learned to code before or after college, rarely during.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Sahil (@shl) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/shl/status/1266731956059824128?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 30, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Kallaway mentioned 3 books in his article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The War of Art: Winning the Inner Creative Battles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Power of Habit: Why We Do What We Do in Life and Business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Obstacle Is the Way: The Timeless Art of Turning Trials into Triumph&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;The War of Art: Winning the Inner Creative Battles&lt;/code&gt; in less than half a day. It’s a small book that’s crystal clear and something that’ll make the reader feel it was written for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s written in 3 parts. The first one deals with the bad guy - &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Resistance&lt;/code&gt;. Alex talks about it in his article. The second one is about how to deal with the bad guy &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Turning Pro&lt;/code&gt;. The third one is about inspiration. The book is a treat for those who are spiritual. If you aren’t, no problem it’ll still teach you many invaluable lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some lessons I have learnt from it and every developer or an aspiring developer needs to know. (I’m not a fan of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;aspiring developer&lt;/code&gt; label. Either you’re a developer or not)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Beating &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;resistance&lt;/code&gt; is not difficult but boring.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steven starts the book with how he spends his day. As a writer, he has to rely on creativity to get going. But, this is where Resistance comes to play. He wins over it by following a routine. Though there’s nothing extraordinary or fancy in it, he describes how he wins over &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;resistance&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a secret that real writers know that wannabe writers don’t, and the secret is this: It’s not the writing part that’s hard. What’s hard is sitting down to write. What keeps us from sitting down is Resistance. - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can get boring to solve javascript coding problems or even learn HTML and CSS. Most of the work that happens in production is boring too. But, the boring tasks need a lot of practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Understand that everyone struggles with &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;resistance&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparison is the thief of joy. It’s easy to compare yourselves to a senior and established developer and feel that you can never be like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, they also went through the same fears, struggles and feelings. Who knows, they may also be going through self-doubt and anxiety! As a developer, your main goal is to learn to code, not focus on what others are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone who has a body experiences Resistance - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not look up and get overwhelmed. If you’re a beginner developer, looking at complex projects and apps can demotivate you. That’s because you’re trying to see the hilltop from a valley. Do not focus on becoming someone. Try to do something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grandiose fantasies are a symptom of Resistance. They’re the sign of an amateur. The professional has learned that success, like happiness, comes as a by-product of work. - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. It’s not a one-day battle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Resistance&lt;/code&gt; has to be fought anew, every day. Not every day is the same. Some days are really overwhelming. Some of you may be learning to code with a full-time job or other responsibilities. Every day is a new day and a chance to move ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had a bad day, yesterday? Forget it and start afresh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RESISTANCE NEVER SLEEPS - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. The best opportunity is most likely one step ahead of your worst setback&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have problems. Some of them seem like the worst and can be devastating. The COVID Pandemic was one that caused a lot of distress at a collective level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, all this can be conquered when you conquer &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Resistance&lt;/code&gt;. Keep this in mind - the fight is not over as long as you’re alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RESISTANCE IS MOST POWERFUL AT THE FINISH LINE - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. Do not Rationalize.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rationalization means &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;attempt to explain or justify (behaviour or an attitude) with logical reasons, even if these are not appropriate&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a developer struggling to learn a new technology or programming language, understand that it’s hard. It’s going to be tough and that should not be an excuse for you to drop it or go in search of an easier technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of you may be trying to juggle a full-time job, personal responsibilities and study. But, remember to keep your eyes on your goal - becoming an expert Developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Resistance leaves out, of course, is that all this mean s diddly. Tolstoy had thirteen kids and wrote War and Peace. - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6. Put yourself out there and cut through criticism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you learning web development? Share your journey publicly. Are you building projects? Talk about it. Make connections. People out there must know you exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be difficult. You may get criticized and mocked by people who don’t even know to write a “Hello World” program. Be your own critic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuals who are realized in their own lives almost never criticize others. If they speak at all, it is to offer encouragement. - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a slight difference between showing off and putting yourself out there. The former is mostly boastful and condescending. It may border being unethical too if you try to show off things that you can’t do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A professional’s work has style; it is distinctively his own. But he doesn’t let his signature grandstand for him. His style serves the material. He does not impose it as a means of drawing attention to himself. - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7. The path to mastery is alone at first but not always&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you embark on a new journey, you may be alone. But, fret not, you’ll soon discover similar people and some may even join you. Keep the faith and go ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the trick: We’re never alone. As soon as we step outside the campfire glow, our Muse lights on our shoulder like a butterfly. The act of courage calls forth infallibly that deeper part of ourselves that supports and sustains us. - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;8. Fall down if you must but once. Not more than that.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may be some bad days that force you to miss practice or work for a day. If it’s something real and needs more than a day - gladly take it. But if it’s lethargy or aimlessness that forces you to do it, don’t skip studying/building for more than a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The professional has learned better. He respects Resistance. He knows if he caves in today, no matter how plausible the pretext, he’ll be twice as likely to cave in tomorrow. - Steven Pressfield (The War of Art)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Payment Gateways for Dummies]]></title><description><![CDATA[Payment gateways are integral to all online transactions. They are the channels through which virtual payments are fulfilled. The process of…]]></description><link>https://ckvignesh.github.io/my-second-post/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://ckvignesh.github.io/my-second-post/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 23:46:37 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Payment gateways are integral to all online transactions. They are the channels through which virtual payments are fulfilled. The process of making an online payment consists of many steps having different components and contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article will serve as a guide to understanding a payment gateway, the services they offer, how it works and the parties to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Payment Gateway?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an online payments service that acts like an entrance or a channel. It’s usually integrated with an e-commerce platform. It can be used for both – receiving and making payments. It has a two-way traffic going through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The customer who uses an e-commerce website for purchases has to fill his details. These include – debit/credit card number, expiry date and the CVV number at the back of the card. By entering this data, the customer gives consent for the payment, implicitly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a payment service provider?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A payment service provider (PSP) is the one who stands between the customer and the seller. A merchant may have his bank account in one bank and the seller may have it in a different one. It would be difficult for such transactions to be fulfilled if they had to deal with the banks directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where a payment service provider comes in. It can connect multiple acquiring banks, financial institutions, payment networks and processors. All the integration between them is automatically handled by the PSP. This becomes very helpful in international transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a merchant account?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A merchant account is a bank account that holds the funds from online or card transactions. This is not the business bank account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To open a merchant bank account, a seller can approach a payment gateway, payment processors, payment service provider; any acquiring banks etc. They can also get it from Independent Sales Organisations and High street banks etc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A merchant identification number is issued to a seller after the application. It’s known as MID which is also an account number for the merchant account. This is the holding account for the seller’s funds from card/online payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merchant accounts play a vital role in maintaining the chain of approval. It’s a long process because there’s a delay between the customer paying money and receiving the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The products can be returned due to any reason. In such cases, this money would have to be refunded to the customer. This is handled automatically by the acquiring bank by deducting money from the merchant account. Most businesses face the risk of returns depending upon the risk in transactions and the nature of your business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A seller may have multiple sources of income – from card payments, online transactions, wallet payments etc. A merchant account simplifies this. The payment gateway collects all the payments in a merchant account. It transfers the money into the business bank account only on the date of settlement. All the payments are combined into one single deposit. This makes reconciliation easy for the business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Payment reconciliation is carried out by checking bank statements against accounting records and the payment gateway, PSP, ISO or acquiring bank’s records to confirm that the payment amounts are correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is the difference between a payment gateway and a merchant account?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A payment gateway is a channel or a pathway for the transaction to occur. It’s the link between the customer’s account and the merchant account. This connection enables the free flow of money between the two bank accounts in a transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a seller, you cannot do an online transaction without a merchant account. This is not similar to a business bank account. It’s a holding account where funds are held till the verification is completed. The seller has little control over this account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get a merchant account opened by your bank, a payment gateway or processor or by any other financial institution. Some payment gateways may not be doing payment processing. It’s preferable to opt for a service that combines both these functions. This brings us to the next question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is the difference between a payment gateway and a payment processor/payment service provider?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The functions of a payment processor and a payment gateway may look alike. They are the channels or intermediaries to fulfil transactions between a merchant account and a customer account.
But they’re not the same. Here’s the difference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A payment gateway is helpful for e-commerce transactions. It’s also necessary for transactions like telephone purchases, digital wallet transactions, card on file payments etc. The point here is that it’s used for transactions which are CNP (Card Not Present).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A payment gateway can honour a transaction without the need of a physical card.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A payment processor, on the other hand, needs a physical card to fulfil a transaction. It’s necessary to have it in cases where a PoS (Point of Sales) machine is used. Card–swiping transactions can be honoured only if there’s a payment processor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are four parties in this transaction – a customer, his issuing bank, the merchant’s account and the acquiring bank.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is the difference between an e-commerce platform and a payment gateway?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An e-commerce platform is an end to end software solution. It can be a website or a mobile application. Online shops and stores need an e-commerce platform to sell their goods or services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An e-commerce store offers – User interface, Store management system, Security, Data consolidation, Support and Payment processing. Some examples of e-commerce platforms are Shopify, BigCommerce, WooCommerce, Wix Stores etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A payment gateway is a channel between the customer’s account and the merchant account. Today, most e-commerce platforms have built-in payment processors, like Shopify Payments is Shopify’s. There are other options like Stripe, Amazon Pay and PayPal too, which can be integrated with Shopify. These are 3rd party Payment Gateways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How does a payment gateway work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A payment gateway provides the link for online transactions for money to flow. Now, this is how the payment gateway works to honour the transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The customer visits the eCommerce website or mobile app and selects a product. After filling in the details, they proceed to checkout and complete the transaction. There are a few options on how it can be done from here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A hosted payment page&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a payment page where the customer will be redirected to, after checking out. They have to enter their card details on this page and complete the transaction over the payment gateway.
Here, the e-commerce platform does not store any payment data. There’s little need for complying with Payment Card Industry (PCI) standards in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A server to server integration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, there are two servers – a merchant’s server and a payment gateway’s server. This is used in cases where the merchant stores payment data before sending it for processing.
This provides a faster fulfilment, better interface and a controlled environment for the customer to enter his payment details. They are redirected to the payment gateway only after entering the payment data. There’s a need to strictly comply with PCI standards here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Encryption at source&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is similar to the server to server integration. But, here there’s a slight difference in how the payment data is stored by the merchant. It permits the merchant to accept payments through the e-commerce platform while encrypting sensitive card data.
This is done by the payment gateway’s encryption library at the browser level. The PCI compliance in this case is much simple than the one before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step for the customer would be to initiate the transaction. They have to enter their debit or credit card details in the columns on the payments page. This page asks the cardholder’s name, the card number, its expiration date and CSC (Card Security Code) or CVV number (Card Verification Value).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data is passed through secure channels onto the payment gateway. This depends on the type of integration in the first step (a hosted payment page, a server to server integration or encryption at source).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The payment gateway encrypts the card details which were entered during checkout. It performs numerous checks to ensure and confirm the authenticity before sending the card data to the acquiring bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The acquiring bank verifies this data and redirects the customer to the card schemes (Some examples of card schemes are Visa, American Express, and MasterCard etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The card schemes receive this data and then perform a verification before sending the payment data to the issuing bank. This is the bank where the customer has his account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issuing bank scrutinises this payment data and approves the transaction if all the details match. The approved payment message is sent from the card schemes to the acquiring bank. If it fails due to any reason, a decline message is sent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The acquiring bank sends the approval or decline message back to the payment gateway. If the payment was approved, the acquirer collects the payment amount from the issuing bank. This money is then held in the merchant account. If it was a decline message, the transaction failure error message would be displayed to the customer. Sometimes, they would be given another option to retry the transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The merchant account now has the money deposited in it. It does not go to the business bank account immediately. This is to safeguard the customer in case he has some issues with the product and would need a refund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of the business receiving its money in the bank account depends on the settlement agreement. This process is called settlement and it’s an agreement between the seller and the payment gateway. The money from different transactions is deposited into the business account a single time, depending on the agreement. In short, if there were 5 customers who bought something from the website in a month, the payment gateway would deposit it as only 1 lump sum amount, in the business bank account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The payment gateway acts as a safeguard for a customer and makes the reconciliation for a seller easier. This whole process takes place in less than 4 – 5 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a card scheme?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A card scheme is a payment network. This network consists of payment cards like debit and credit cards. The financial institutions become members of these networks to issue cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are mainly 2 card schemes – open and closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The open card scheme has 3 parties – Cardholder, Merchant and Franchisee. A franchisee acts as an issuing bank and an acquiring bank. Diner’s club, American Express and Discover Card follow this model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closed scheme has 4 parties – cardholder, Issuer Bank, Merchant account and acquiring bank. Visa, MasterCard, UnionPay and RuPay follow this model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Payment gateway costs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typical costs associated with payment gateways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt; One time Set-up Fee: £0 - £30&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
This is a onetime fee during set-up of the payment gateway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt; Monthly Fee: £20 - £250&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Recurring monthly fee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt; Transaction Flat Fee: 1.4% + 10p to 3.4% + 20p&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
It’s calculated per transaction and can vary depending on the volume of sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt; PCI Annual Management Fee: Approx £30&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Paid for storing data to comply with the PCI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt; Transaction Rate: 0.75% to 3%&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Charged by the merchant account provider&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to choose a payment gateway provider?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing a payment gateway or a payment service provider is a tough decision. It boils down to the needs of the business, its budgeting, margins and risk of returns. The following are some generic points to consider before opting for one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When do you want to start accepting payments?
Having a merchant account is mandatory for many Payment gateway/Service providers. It may take 3 weeks to a month for all the procedures to be completed and get a merchant ID allotted.
But, some payment service providers like Strip and PayPal allow you to accept payments without a merchant account. That’s because they come with a built-in feature which works like a merchant account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much can you want to spend on a payment gateway?
The price of the service is important for a business. That’s because if the cost on a payment service exceeds the margins, it would affect its price. There are a lot of costs associated with online transactions, like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;· Set-up costs
· Transaction costs
· Maintenance fees
· Administration costs
· Conversion Fees etc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there are some penalty fees for chargebacks. All of these can make it an expensive affair. A small business must consider direct debit as an alternative because it’s cheaper than this.
Popular Payment Gateway and Service Providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a previous section, the difference between a PSP and a Payment Gateway was explained. In the real world, there are mostly pure payment gateways or payment service providers. PSPs also perform the role of a payment gateway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a list of popular payment gateways. They provide services only for online or non-card present transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Braintree&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Braintree provides mobile and web payments for ecommerce stores. It provides merchant accounts for each individual seller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Authorize.net&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It allows sellers to accept digital payments in their merchant accounts. It also allows them to accept electronic checks. It’s a subsidiary of Visa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Windcave (PaymentExpress)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windcave is a PCI compliant payment gateway service. It’s an international service which accepts payments from debit and credit cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;TrustCommerce&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TrustCommerce is known for its omni channel solutions. It lets users accept payments from cards, wallets and much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a list of popular payment service providers. They work in both cases – non card present transactions and the ones which need a card swipe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stripe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stripe was built exclusively for internet businesses. It’s a referred payments processor by many big brands. It lets you accept payments without a merchant account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;PayPal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PayPal is a popular brand among most new players in the internet business. It’s the most convenient option for them as it lets them accept payments without a merchant account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Adyen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adyen is known for its terminals. They are centralized with one platform for mobile, web and physical transactions. This acts as a crime deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sage Pay&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sage Pay is commonly used in Europe. It’s known for its security features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Venmo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s owned by PayPal and offers a social network as well. It’s a peer to peer digital service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to Look For In a Payment Gateway:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the factors you need to look for in a Payment gateway, before choosing them. This is a purely technical aspect of looking at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Uptime and Reliability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecommerce stores work round the clock. So, if the payment gateway fails, it is equivalent to the shop staying closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Real-Time Status check&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some payment gateways and service providers offer real-time status of the business. This may not be part of all the packages. But, it becomes useful when the sellers want to analyse and solve problems in business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accepting Multiple Payment Options and Currencies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecommerce stores see visitors from different countries having different payment gateway or service providers. So, this becomes essential to have this available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Integration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the flexibility of a payment gateway that permits integration to the e-commerce platform. Some websites have an e-commerce platform, a content management system and a shopping card together. This is where integration becomes pivotal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fraud Detection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Payment gateways offer fraud detection too. No merchant would want a customer who buys something to use and return it. This happens in the case of informational products like books, movies etc.
At the same time, they would not want to drive away legitimate buyers. Payment gateways reject payments from such blacklisted customers by recognizing their cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PCI DSS Compliance Level&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They stand for Payment Card Industry Data Security Standard. These are standards that have to be followed to keep customer data safe. Loss of such data can adversely impact a business. Prefer a payment gateway provider that accepts PCI DSS Level 1 standards.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>